A Guide to the Shackelford Family Papers 1899-1960
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Shackelford Family Papers 1899-1960
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
3525-ak
This collection consists of ca. 300 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was deposited by George Green Shackelford of Blacksburg, Virginia, on 10 August 1977.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Shackelford family resided at "Willow Grove" in Orange, Virginia. Virginius Randolph Shackelford (1885-1949) married Peachy Gascoigne Lyne (1887-1976) at St. Thomas Episcopal Church, on 10 November 1910. They had four sons: Virginius Randolph Shackelford (died an infant, 1911); Lyne Moncure Shackelford (b. 1914), Virginius Randolph Shackelford, Jr. (b. 1916), and George Green Shackelford (b. 1920).
Virginius R. Shackelford attended Woodberry Forest Preparatory School and the University of Virginia from which he received his B.A. and LL.B. He was admitted to the Virginia bar in 1907 and practiced law in Orange and Staunton, Virginia until his death in 1949. His wife, Peachy Gascoigne Lyne, was the daughter of William Henry Lyne (ca. 1840-1888) and Cassandra Oliver Moncure (1945-1934; m. 1868).
Scope and Content Information
This collection of Shackelford family papers consists of ca. 300 items, 1899-1960. It includes correspondence, genealogical material, newspaper clippings, and photographs. The manuscripts consist primarily of the correspondence of Virginius Shackelford and Peachy Shackelford (Mrs. Virginius) and of genealogical material regarding the Lyne family. The 1938 collection of letters from Virginius Shackelford to his three sons written during a European tour provides a particularly interesting description of pre-war Germany. The printed material includes a collection of newspaper clippings concerning the Shackelford family and other items of historical interest. Programs and a 1915 publication, "Songs" of the University of Virginia Summer School, are also included in the printed material.
Organization
The collection was divided into two series: manuscripts and printed material. Manuscripts include correspondence and genealogical material. Newspaper clippings, magazines, and programs comprise printed material. Items within each series were arranged chronologically. A small group of unidentified photographs were placed at the end of the collection.
Contents List
- Manuscript Material
  - Correspondence: George Shackelford to "Kate" 1899 Jun 14 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: primarily of Virginius Shackelford and Peachy Shackelford (Mrs. Virginius) 1904-1948 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Virginius R. Shackelford to his sons re European trip 1938 Jul 12 - 1938 Aug 7 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: primarily of Virginius Shackelford and Peachy Shackelford (Mrs. Virginius) n.d. (Box 1)
  - Genealogical material re Lyne Family, Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 1)
  - Speeches, Pamphlets, Notes re Dolly Madison Garden Club, Alexandria, Virginia 1930-1936 (Box 1)
- Printed Material
  - Magazines 1905-1958 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1904-1960 and n.d. (Box 1)
    5 folders
  - Programs 1940-1958 (Box 1)
  - "Songs" of the University of Virginia Summer School 1915 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 1)
  - Photographs n.d. (Box 1)